We live in a time of fear,
نحن نعيش فى عصر الخوف،
and our response to fear can either be to contract
وتكون استجابتنا للخوف إما أن ننغلق
and attempt to guard ourselves
ونحاول حماية أنفسنا
or to extend ourselves, hold on to each other,
أو أن ننفتح وندعم بعضنا البعض،
and face our fears together.
ونواجه مخاوفنا معًا.
What is your instinct?
ما هى غريزتك؟
What do you see more of in the world?
ما هو أكثر شيء تراه بالعالم؟
The problem with the first approach
المشكلة فى أسلوب تعاملنا الأول
is that in our mounting isolation,
هي عزلتنا المتزايدة،
we divide ourselves from others.
نبعد أنفسنا عن الآخرين.
Our sense of isolation grows,
يكبر إحساسنا بالعزلة،
because our imagination goes into overdrive
لأن خيالنا يتضاعف
about the people and the spaces that we no longer engage with.
حول الأشخاص والأماكن التي لم نعد نتعامل معها.
Our sense of otherness grows, and we lose empathy.
يتزايد إحساسنا بالاختلاف، ونفقد التعاطف.
Today I'm going to tell you about a group of people
سأتحدث اليوم عن مجموعة من الأشخاص
that took the global challenge of terrorism
الذين واجهوا التحدي العالمي الذي يفرضه الإرهاب
and began creating spaces where strangers connect in solidarity.
وبدأوا فى إنشاء ساحات حيث يتجمع الغرباء فى تضامن.
My own obsession with what I see as irrational divisions began as a child.
بدأ لدي هاجس مما آراه من الانقسامات اللامنطقية منذ الطفولة.
As a fourth-generation Kenyan Muslim of Indian origin,
أنحدر من الجيل الرابع من مسلمي (كينيا) من أصل هندي،
it bothered me that in four generations,
أزعجنى أنه خلال أربعة أجيال،
there wasn't a single marriage in my family
لم يكن هناك زواجٌ واحدٌ فى عائلتي
outside of my small religious community.
خارج نطاق مجتمعنا الإسلامي الصغير.
And I wondered what that was about.
وتساءلت لماذا كان ذلك؟
Was it fear?
هل كان الخوف؟
Was it racism?
هل كانت العنصرية؟
Was it cultural preservation?
هل كان الحفاظ على الثقافة؟
Did it have something to do with colonialism?
هل كان لذلك علاقة بالاستعمار؟
Certainly, we didn't share a lot of the same public spaces with others.
بالطبع، لم نتمكن من مشاركة الكثير من الأماكن العامة ذاتها مع الآخرين.
These divisions bothered me deeply, and they drove my career choices.
أزعجتني هذا الانقسامات بشدة، وتحكمت فى خياراتي المهنية.
When I was 20, the US embassies in Kenya and Tanzania were bombed.
عندما كنت فى العشرين، تم تفجير السفارة الأمريكية في (كينيا) و(تنزانيا).
A year later, I was on my way to the Middle East
في العام التالي، توجهت إلى الشرق الأوسط
to study conflict resolution.
لدراسة حل النزاعات.
And then from that point on,
ومن تلك المرحلة فصاعدًا،
it wasn't very hard for me to find insecure environments to work in,
كان من الصعب العثور على بيئة عمل آمنة
because the world was quickly shifting
لأن العالم كان ينتقل بسرعة
in what we now know as the time of terrorism.
إلى ما نعرفه الآن بوقت الإرهاب.
I was in Washington, DC when 9/11 happened,
كنت في (واشنطن) وقت أحداث 11 سبتمبر،
and then I moved back home to Kenya to work with refugees
ثم عدت أدراجى إلى وطني (كينيا) للعمل مع اللاجئين
and then later worked in Pakistan
وعملت بعد ذلك في (باكستان)
and in Afghanistan.
وفي (أفغانستان).
In all of these places, what I noticed
لاحظت في جميع هذه البلاد
was how important physical spaces are
مدى أهمية أماكن العبادة
to making us feel safe
في أن تجعلنا نشعر بالأمان
and well
والراحة
and like we belong.
ونحب انتمائنا إليها.
In 2013, I came back home to Nairobi from Afghanistan.
عُدت إلى (نيروبي) من (أفغانستان) عام 2013.
Al-Shabaab operatives had besieged Westgate shopping center,
حاصر ناشطون من "حركة الشباب" المركز التجاري (ويست جيت)،
killing 67 people in a day of utter horror.
مما أسفر عن مقتل 67 شخصًا في يوم من الرعب التام.
Soon after that,
بعد ذلك بوقت قصير،
I could see how Nairobi was beginning to change,
رأيت كيف بدأت (نيروبي) في التغيّر،
and it was beginning to feel more like the fear and terror-weary
وكان بداية الإحساس بمزيد من الخوف في المدن التي أنهكها الإرهاب
and war-torn cities that I had worked in.
ومزقتها الحرب والتي عملت بها.
And Nairobi continues to grow in fear-driven ways.
وتستمر (نيروبي) في النمو بأساليب يحركها الخوف.
We see more walls, more barriers,
نرى العديد من الحوائط العازلة والحواجز،
more security.
والمزيد من أفراد الأمن.
And like other parts of the world,
ومثل أي جزء بالعالم،
we are experiencing an erosion of human connection.
نحن نعاني من تآكل في التواصل البشري.
Divisions along religious lines are deepening,
تتعمق الانقسامات على أساس الانتماء الديني،
and we're doubting more and more how much we have in common.
ونحن نتساءل أكثر وأكثر عن عدد الأمور المشتركة بيننا.
We are at a pivotal time
نحن في وقت حاسم
when we need to restore our confidence in humanity
نحتاج فيه إلى استرجاع ثقتنا في الإنسانية
and stand boldly and visibly together.
والوقوف معًا بجرأة وبشكل واضح.
So in 2014, I brought together a group of people in Nairobi
لذلك أحضرت عام 2104 مجموعة من الأشخاص إلى (نيروبي)
to figure out what to do:
لمعرفة ما علينا فعله:
public intellectuals, diplomats, artists, development workers.
المثقفون والدبلوماسيون والفنانون والعاملون على التنمية.
And the group articulated our challenge as threefold:
أرجعت المجموعة التحدي الذي نواجهه إلى ثلاثة جوانب:
one, to reclaim the city from the narrative of terrorism
الأول، استعادة المدينة من السرد المتعلق بالإرهاب
and back into the hands of the people that live there;
والعودة إلى مساعدة الناس التي تعيش هناك،
two, introduce a language beyond race, tribe or religion
الثاني، إيجاد لغة بعيدة عن العرق والقبلية والدين
that would help us transcend our differences;
وهذا سوف يساعدنا على تجاوز اختلافاتنا،
and three, provide a gesture that would help restore empathy
الثالث، اللفتة الطيبة التي تساعد في إعادة التعاطف
and conversation and trust.
والحوار والثقة.
One of the people in this group was an artist and architect,
أحد أعضاء هذه المجموعة كان فنان ومعماري،
Yazmany Arboleda.
(يزماني أربوليدا).
He and I have collaborated in other parts of the world
تعاونت معه في مناطق كثيرة فى العالم
over many years.
لسنوات عديدة.
He has a history
له تاريخ
of disrupting urban environments
من العمل في البيئات الحضرية المضطربة
and making strangers connect
ويقرب الغرباء من بعضهم
in incredible, beautiful and spectacular ways.
بطرق جميلة ومذهلة.
He had an idea.
كانت لديه فكرة.
The idea was to unite people of different faiths
وهي توحيد الناس ذوي العقائد المختلفة
by getting them to paint each other's houses of worship,
من خلال طلاء دور عبادة بعضهم البعض،
mosques, temples, synagogues, churches,
المساجد والمعابد والكُنس اليهودية والكنائس،
paint them yellow
يطلونها باللون الأصفر
in the name of love.
باسم الحب.
By focusing on icons of faith,
بالتركيز على أيقونات العقيدة،
we would get people to reexamine the true essence of their faith,
سوف يدرك الناس الجوهر الحقيقي لعقائدهم،
the common belief that we share in kindness, generosity and friendship.
الاعتقاد الشائع هو أننا ننشر العطف والطيبة والصداقة.
By creating pathways between houses of worship
بإنشاء ممرات بين دور العبادة
within one neighborhood,
داخل الحي الواحد،
we would create islands of stability
سنخلق جُزُرًا من الاستقرار
and networks of people
وشبكة من الناس
that could withstand threats.
التي بإمكانها أن تصمد أمام التهديدات.
And neighbors, by picking up a paintbrush with other neighbors,
وعند إمساك الجيران لفرشاة الطلاء مع آخرين،
would engage not just with their heads
لن يتشاركوا فقط برؤوسهم
but with their hands and with their hearts.
بل بسواعدهم وقلوبهم أيضًا.
And the painted buildings would become sculptures in the landscape
وستصبح المباني المطلية بمثابة منحوتات على أرض الطبيعة
that speak of people from very different backgrounds
تتحدث عن اُناس ذوي خلفيات مختلفة جدًا
that stand together.
وقفوا سويًا.
We'd call the project "Colour in Faith."
أطلقنا على المشروع اسم "لون الإيمان."
We loved the idea and we immediately began approaching houses of worship:
أحببنا الفكرة وبدأنا على الفور دخول دور العبادة.
churches, temples, mosques, synagogues.
كنائس ومعابد ومساجد وكُنس يهودية،
Door to door, we went to more than 60 rabbis,
من باب إلى آخر، ذهبنا لأكثر من 60 حاخام،
imams, pastors and priests.
وأئمة وقساوسة وكهنة.
As you can imagine,
ولكم أن تتخيلوا،
bringing these communities together
جمع هذه المجتمعات معًا
when prejudices are reinforced by a global pandemic of fear
مع وجود أحكام مسبقة معززة بوباء عالمي اسمه الخوف
is not easy.
ليس بالأمر السهل.
It was complicated.
كان أمرًا معقدًا.
We were confronted with the hierarchy of decision-making
لقد واجهنا التسلسل الهرمي لصنع القرار
within religious establishments.
داخل المؤسسات الدينية.
For example, with Catholic churches,
على سبيل المثال، في الكنائس الكاثوليكية،
we were told that the archbishop would have to make the decision.
قيل لنا أن رئيس الأساقفة هو من سيتخذ القرار،
And so we wrote a letter to the archbishop.
ولهذا كتبنا خطابًا لرئيس الأساقفة.
We wrote a letter to the Vatican.
كتبنا خطابًا لـ(الفاتيكان).
We're still waiting to hear back.
ومازلنا فى انتظار الرد.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And with other houses of worship,
وبالنسبة إلى دور العبادة الأخرى،
we were told that the patrons, the people that pay for the building
قيل لنا أن الرعاة الذين يدفعون للدار
and the construction and the painting of the buildings
وعمليات البناء وطلاء الأبنية
would have to make a decision.
هم من عليهم اتخاذ القرار.
And then we came head-to-head
تقابلنا وجهًا لوجه
with the long legacy of missionary and donor dependence
مع من لهم باع طويل في التبشير والاعتماد على المانحين
that so impedes unconditional civic action,
الذي يُعيق العمل المدني غير المشروط،
and we learned this the hard way.
وتعلمنا ذلك بالطريقة الصعبة.
There was one community
كان هناك مجتمع واحد
that in our repeated conversations would keep asking us
فى كل حواراتنا المتكررة ظل يطلب منا
to appreciate them.
أن نقدّرهم.
And so we would keep going back
ولذا سوف نعود
and telling them that we appreciate them,
ونخبرهم بأننا نقدرهم،
and of course,
وبالطبع،
if we didn't appreciate them, we wouldn't be here.
لو لم نقدرهم، لما كنا هنا.
And then we learned painfully late in the game
ثم علمنا مع الأسف في وقت متأخر من هذه اللعبة
that the word "appreciation" is code for getting paid to participate.
أن كلمة " تقدير" هي شفرة لدفع المال مقابل مشاركتهم.
And so we challenged them
ومن ثم تحديناهم
and we asked the question,
وطرحنا السؤال،
"So what will it cost?
"كم سيتكلف؟
How much could we pay you?
كم سندفع لكم؟
And if we pay for your faith, is it really faith?"
وإذا دفعنا لإيمانكم، أيكون هذا إيمانًا حقًا؟"
We started the project asking the question,
بدأنا المشروع نسأل السؤال،
"Where does your faith live?"
"أين يكمن إيمانك؟"
And here we found ourselves asking the question,
وهنا وجدنا أنفسنا نسأل،
"How much does your faith cost?"
"كم يُكلف إيمانك؟"
But the most difficult issue was the perceived risk of standing apart.
لكن القضية الأصعب كانت خطر الوقوف جانبًا.
We had one synagogue that flat-out refused to participate
كان لدينا كنيس يهودي رفض المشاركة بشكل صريح
because it feared drawing attention to itself
لأنه يخشى أن يلفت الانتباه
and becoming a target.
ويصبح مستهدفًا.
Similarly, we had a mosque that also feared becoming a target.
بالمثل، كان لدينا مسجد يخشى أيضًا أن يكون مستهدفًا.
And these fears are justified.
وهذه مخاوف مبررة.
And yet, there were 25 houses of worship that pledged to participate.
ومع ذلك، تعهدت 25 من دور العبادة بالمشاركة في المشروع.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
These bold leaders took the gesture and reinforced it with their own meaning.
اتخذ هؤلاء القادة الشجعان زمام المبادرة وعززوها بمعنى ذاتي.
For some, it was to tell the world that they're not terrorists.
فمثّلت للبعض رسالة للعالم أنهم ليسوا إرهابيين.
For others, it was to welcome people through their doors to ask questions.
ولآخرين كانت ترحيبًا لطرح أسئلة الناس.
And for some, it was to bridge the gap
وكانت لآخرين سد الفجوة
between the older and the younger generation,
بين كبار السن والجيل الأصغر سنًا،
which by the way is something that many faiths are grappling with right now.
وهو الأمر الذي تعاني منه العديد من المعتقدات حتى الآن.
And for some it was simply to build neighborhood solidarity
وكان للبعض بمثابة بناء حي متماسك
in advance of feared election violence.
قبل الخوف من العنف الانتخابي.
When asked why yellow,
عند طرح سؤال لماذا الأصفر؟
one imam beautifully said,
أجاب أحد الأئمة بطريقة جميلة،
"Yellow is the color of the sun.
" الأصفر هو لون الشمس.
The sun shines on us all equally.
تشرق الشمس علي جميع البشر بالتساوي.
It does not discriminate."
لا تميّز بين أحد."
He and others spread the word through their congregations
نشر هو وآخرون هذه العبارة من خلال تجمعاتهم
and over the radio.
وعبر أثير الإذاعة.
Municipal government officials stepped forward and helped
تقدم مسؤولو حكومة البلدية لتقديم يد العون
with permits and with convening civil society organizations.
فيما يخص التصاريح وانعقاد منظمات المجتمع المدني.
A paint company donated a thousand liters of yellow paint
تبرعت شركة طلاء بـ 1000 لتر من الطلاء الأصفر.
mixed especially for us in what they now call "optimistic yellow."
تم خلطه خصيصًا لنا وما يسمونه الآن "الأصفر المتفائل."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And a poetry collective joined forces with a university
كما وحّدت جماعة شعر جهودها مع إحدى الجامعة
and hosted a series of tweet chats
واستضافت سلسلة من التغريدات
that challenged the nation on issues of faith,
التي واجهت الأمة في القضايا المتعلقة بالدين،
our faith not just in the context of religion,
عقائدنا، ليس فقط في سياق الدين،
but our faith in politicians and tribe and nation,
لكن أيضًا عقائدنا حول رجال السياسة والقبيلة والأمة،
our faith in the older generation and in the younger generation.
إيماننا بالجيل القديم والجديد.
And then Colour in Faith was launched at a gallery event
أُطلق مشروع "لون الإيمان" ضمن معرض فني
that invited an incredible mix of gallerygoers
والذي ضم عددًا هائلًا من رواد المعارض
and religious leaders and artists and businesspeople.
ورجال الدين والفنانين ورجال الأعمال.
Already, even before picking up a paintbrush,
حينذاك، وقبل التقاط فرشاة الطلاء،
we had accomplished so much of the conversation and connection
أجرينا العديد من المحادثات والاتصالات
that we had hoped for.
وهذا ما تمنيناه.
And then we began to paint.
وبعدها بدأنا الطلاء،
Muslims stood by Christians
وقف المسلمون بجوار المسيحيين
and atheists and agnostics and Hindus
والملحدين واللاأدريين والهندوس
and painted a mosque yellow.
وقاموا بطلاء المسجد باللون الأصفر.
And then they all came together again and painted a church yellow,
وبعد ذلك عادوا معًا مجددًا وقاموا بطلاء الكنيسة بالأصفر.
and then another mosque,
ثم مسجدًا آخر،
and then another church.
ثم كنيسة أخرى.
Poets and musicians performed while we painted.
قدم الشعراء والموسيقيون عروضهم أثناء عملية الطلاء.
We painted in Nairobi,
قمنا بالطلاء فى (نيروبي)،
and then we painted in Mombasa.
ثم (مومباسا).
The local and international press did features on Colour in Faith
أجرت الصحافة المحلية والدولية تحقيقات صحفية عن "لون الإيمان"
in English and French and Swahili
باللغة الإنجليزية والفرنسية والسواحيلية
and Spanish and Somali.
والإسبانية والصومالية.
CNN highlighted Colour in Faith as a way of bringing communities together.
سلّطت (سي إن إن) الضوء على "لون الإيمان" كطريقة لربط المجتمعات ببعضها البعض.
And our social media platforms lit up,
أُضيئت منصات وسائل الإعلام الاجتماعي لدينا،
connecting more and more people.
عاملةً على ربط المزيد من الأشخاص.
And these neighbors continued to stay in touch.
واستمر هؤلاء الجيران في التواصل.
There are some that are pursuing politics with a platform of peace,
هناك بعض من يتابع السياسة من منصة السلام،
and we have communities as far as Argentina and the US
ولدينا مجتمعات بعيدة مثل (الأرجنتين) و(الولايات المتحدة)
and as close as Mali and Rwanda
وقريبة مثل (مالي) و(رواندا)
that are asking for our help.
يريدون مساعدتنا.
And we would love to help.
ونود أن نقدم المساعدة.
It's our dream that this project, this idea, spreads across the world,
حلمنا أن ينتشر مشروعنا وفكرتنا في جميع أنحاء العالم،
with or without our support.
بدعمنا أو بدونه.
Colour in Faith is literally highlighting those who mean well in yellow.
يمثل لون الإيمان حرفيًا تسليطًا للضوء على أصحاب النوايا الحسنة باللون الأصفر.
Colour in Faith is binding neighborhoods together,
يربط لون الإيمان الأحياء ببعضها البعض،
and it's our hope that when threats come knocking,
وهذا هو أملنا عندما يدق الخطر على الأبواب،
they will collectively sift fact from rumor
أنهم سوف يتحرون الشائعات معًا
and stand in solidarity.
ويقفون معًا متضامنين.
We've proven that the human family can come together and send a message
لقد أثبتنا أن بني البشر يمكن أن يتحدوا سويًا ويبعثوا رسالة
far brighter and more powerful
أكثر إشراقًا وتأثيرًا
than the voices of those that wish to do us harm.
من الأصوات التي تريد إلحاق الضرر بنا.
Though fear is infectious,
على الرغم من أن الخوف مُعدٍ،
we are showing that so is hope.
فنحن نظهر أن هذا هو الأمل.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)